<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Edirom/WeGA-ODD/master/schema/de/wegaWritings.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Edirom/WeGA-ODD/master/schema/de/wegaWritings.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="T030038.xml"
     xml:base="https://id.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/schnitzler/bahrschnitzler/texts"
     prev="https://id.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/schnitzler/bahrschnitzler/texts/T030037.xml"
     next="https://id.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/schnitzler/bahrschnitzler/texts/T030039.xml">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Hermann Bahr – Arthur Schnitzler: Briefwechsel, Aufzeichnungen, Dokumente 1891–1931</title>
            <title level="a" ref="pmb30339">Hermann Bahr: A Letter From Germany, Dezember 1922</title>
            <author ref="pmb10815">Bahr, Hermann</author>
            <editor>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">Ifkovits, Kurt</name>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">Müller, Martin Anton</name>
            </editor>
            <funder>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">FWF – Fonds für Wissenschaft und Forschung</name>
               <address>
                  <street>Sensengasse 1</street>
                  <postCode>1090 Wien</postCode>
                  <placeName>
                     <country>A</country>
                     <settlement>Wien</settlement>
                  </placeName>
               </address>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>HBAS</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transkription und Kommentierung</resp>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">Kurt Ifkovits</name>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">Martin Anton Müller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Theatermuseum, Wien</publisher>
            <idno type="HBAS-T" n="038"/>
            <availability status="free">
               <p part="N">Copyright © 2017</p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="handle">https://hdl.handle.net/21.11115/0000-000E-8A94-F</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <origDate when="1922-12-00" n="1">Dezember 1922</origDate>
            <listBibl>
               <biblStruct>
                  <analytic>
                     <author ref="pmb10815">Bahr, Hermann</author>
                     <title level="a" ref="pmb30339">A Letter From Germany</title>
                  </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title level="j" ref="pmb29705">The London Mercury</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <date when="1922-12">Dezember 1922</date>
                     </imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="jg">7</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="nr">38</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="pp">194–196</biblScope>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en-UK">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="candidate">
         <change when="2016-02-25" who="MAM">Angelegt.</change>
         <change who="KI MAM" when="2016-09-27">Kollationiert</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="article">
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>A LETTER FROM GERMANY</head>
            <p rend="right" part="N">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  <rs type="place" ref="pmb45258">Munich</rs>
               </hi>.</p>
            <p part="N">
               <rs type="person" ref="pmb2121">ARTHUR SCHNITZLER</rs>’S sixtieth birthday was celebrated in <rs type="place" ref="pmb151">German</rs> theatres by performances of his plays and in the newspapers by friendly appreciations. Admiration was almost always mingled with a sort of sadness–almost as though obituary notices were written rather than congratulations. The <hi rend="italic">
                  <rs type="org" ref="pmb29212">Neue Rundschau</rs>
               </hi> in <rs type="place" ref="pmb168">Berlin</rs>, the organ of his loyal publisher, <rs type="person" ref="pmb11324">S. Fischer</rs>, and the <hi rend="italic">
                  <rs type="org" ref="pmb29404">Moderne Welt</rs>
               </hi> of <rs type="place" ref="pmb50">Vienna</rs> issued »<rs type="person" ref="pmb2121">Schnitzler</rs> numbers.« They opened their pages to his friends and fellow-workers, that on this anniversary they might express their appreciation. Hardly a single one of the famous German names was lacking, but among these good wishes too, a melancholy note was characteristic. Everyone was sincere and glad, and yet there was a funereal air about the entire <rs type="person" ref="pmb2121">Schnitzler</rs> Festival. All of us hoped that he would remain working in our midst for many years to come in the best of health, but we also felt that <rs type="person" ref="pmb2121">Schnitzler</rs>’s works are the expression of an epoch that is gone, irrevocably gone. For that very reason his works are so significant to us, even more so than when they were written. Then the world whose melancholy reflection they were was still in existence; few of us would have dreamed that we would survive it. But <rs type="person" ref="pmb2121">Schnitzler</rs> in some mysterious way anticipated the end even then. He, the physician by profession, saw the Hippocratic lines in the soft face of our amiable <rs type="place" ref="pmb41240">Austrian</rs> heedlessness. The charm of his plays as well as of his stories lies in their unforced gaiety. The <rs type="place" ref="pmb41240">Austrians</rs> retained this characteristic even when the other <rs type="place" ref="pmb151">German</rs> tribes, one after another were becoming self-complacent in a stiff, really quite <rs type="place" ref="pmb151">un-German</rs> dignity. <rs type="place" ref="pmb50">Vienna</rs> seemed the last German city which had not forgotten how to smile. And at that time the only complaint <rs type="place" ref="pmb50">Vienna</rs> had to make of <rs type="person" ref="pmb2121">Schnitzler</rs> was that suddenly secret tears always mingled with his smile. For many years the critics of <rs type="place" ref="pmb50">Vienna</rs> incessantly admonished him. His talent, they maintained, lay fundamentally in his lightheartedness, and yet in all his plays he suddenly allowed himself to be led astray by a serious or even a tragic note which was not his <hi rend="italic">forte</hi> at all. For years <rs type="place" ref="pmb50">Viennese</rs> criticism incessantly called upon him to write »the German comedy.« This cry for »the <rs type="place" ref="pmb151">German</rs> comedy« has long been one of the <hi rend="italic">bravura</hi> »stunts« of German criticism. No matter how many comedies one may write, still it is never <hi rend="italic">the</hi> mythical German comedy. How many a time after a <hi rend="italic">première</hi> didn’t <rs type="person" ref="pmb2121">Schnitzler</rs> complain of this! I recommended:</p>
            <p part="N">»Why not do them the favour? For once put aside your melancholy inclinations; it is usully in the third act that you can’t resist them any longer!«</p>
            <p part="N">And to be sure, he came along after a couple of months when we met again, beaming:</p>
            <p part="N">»This time I am doing it. I am writing the piece for which you have been crying for years. There won’t be a melancholy note in it; this time it will be the long desired German comedy!«</p>
            <p part="N">I wished him »good luck,« and when we saw each other again after a few weeks my first question was:</p>
            <p part="N">»How is the German comedy getting on?«<pb/>
            </p>
            <p part="N">He looked at at me hesitatingly and said:</p>
            <p part="N">»I’ve been very busily at it; I am already down at the <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="KT038-1">last act, only, you know, unfortunately in the preceding act one of the characters committed suicide</anchor>. There was no other way out.« </p>
            <p part="N">And so it happened that up to the present day he has not yet written the much-wanted <rs type="place" ref="pmb151">German</rs> comedy. But to-day we know that the dark shadows surrounding the <rs type="place" ref="pmb41240">Austrian</rs> lightheartedness of his characters were the most genuine part. Deep down <rs type="person" ref="pmb2121">Schnitzler</rs> knew, without admitting it to himself, that <rs type="place" ref="pmb50">Vienna</rs> during the years from 1890 to the War already bore the kiss of death upon its brow. <rs type="place" ref="pmb50">Vienna</rs> is still standing, the houses are still standing, but the Empire whose capital it was is gone. <rs type="place" ref="pmb50">Vienna</rs> has become a fairy-tale without a country. <rs type="person" ref="pmb2121">Schnitzler</rs> always felt <rs type="place" ref="pmb50">Vienna</rs> as a fairy-tale, even when we others were still thinking it was reality. This lends a charm to his works which will not fade, as long as any remembrance remains anywhere in the world of the old Imperial city on the <geogName type="river" instant="false">Danube</geogName>. After all, it always has been <rs type="place" ref="pmb41240">Austria</rs>’s destiny to find its fulfilment only in art. In <rs type="person" ref="pmb12303">Mozart</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="pmb12729">Schubert</rs>, <anchor type="textConst" xml:id="TT038-1">
                  <rs type="person" ref="pmb11024">Bruckner</rs>
               </anchor>, <rs type="person" ref="pmb13152">Hugo Wolf</rs>, and <rs type="person" ref="pmb12163">Mahler</rs> is represented a reality beside which even the historical reality of <rs type="place" ref="pmb41240">Austria</rs> grows pale and sketchy. The life of <rs type="place" ref="pmb41240">Austria</rs> was perhaps always only a rehearsal for its works of art. It is thus that we few remaining <rs type="place" ref="pmb41240">Austrians</rs> whose Fatherland disappeared beneath our feet seek to comfort ourselves.</p>
            <p part="N">
               <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="KT038-2">A very curious work</anchor> on <rs type="person" ref="pmb10806">Johann Sebastian Bach</rs>’s <rs type="work" ref="pmb31825">
                  <hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue</hi>
               </rs> which appeared first in <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="KT038-3">
                  <rs type="work" subtype="implied" ref="pmb32792">extracts</rs>
               </anchor> in the <rs type="org" ref="pmb29704">
                  <hi rend="italic">Preussische Jahrbücher</hi>
               </rs>, has now been published in its <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="KT038-4">entirety</anchor> under the imprint of <rs type="org" ref="pmb29709">Georg Stilke</rs> of <rs type="place" ref="pmb168">Berlin</rs>. It is arousing much attention, and on the one hand is praised quite as much as it is attacked on the other. Its author is <rs type="person" ref="pmb3715">Heinrich Sitte</rs>, the archæologist, of the <rs type="place" ref="pmb617">University of Innsbruck</rs>. There has been much shaking of heads among the »experts.« The professional musicians ask what title has an archæologist to enter a discussion about <rs type="person" ref="pmb10806">Bach</rs>, and the professional archæologists take the view that it is unseemly that one of their colleagues should be coquetting with Dame Music. Both sides had to be reminded that the famous <rs type="person" ref="pmb12303">Mozart</rs> authority, <rs type="person" ref="pmb4203">Otto Jahn</rs>, was also an archæologist by profession. <rs type="person" ref="pmb12793">Camillo Sitte</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="pmb3715">Heinrich</rs>’s father, was both architect and teacher of art; he organised the <rs type="place" ref="pmb693">
                  <hi rend="italic">Staatsgewerbeschule</hi>
               </rs> of <rs type="place" ref="pmb50">Vienna</rs>, and wrote the famous book on »<anchor type="commentary" xml:id="KT038-5">
                  <rs type="work" ref="pmb31823">City Building</rs>
               </anchor>,« which made an entire generation realise again that every proper square in a city, even every street corner, must be arranged according to definite laws, though, of course, unconsciously. <rs type="person" ref="pmb12793">Camillo Sitte</rs>’s most intimate friend was <rs type="person" ref="pmb12521">Hans Richter</rs>, the <rs type="person" ref="pmb13024">Wagner</rs> conductor, and so young <rs type="person" ref="pmb3715">Heinrich</rs> grew up in the midst of both the plastic and musical arts. He was a thoroughly trained pianist, just about ready to appear in public for the first time, when finally he unexpectedly decided in favour of science. If <rs type="person" ref="pmb10806">Bach</rs> was the last word to him in music, so in archæology all his efforts were directed towards the <rs type="work" ref="pmb31819">frieze of the Parthenon</rs>. <rs type="person" ref="pmb28465">Phidias</rs> to him is for the eye what <rs type="person" ref="pmb10806">Bach</rs> is for the ear. He, as it were, regards the <rs type="work" ref="pmb31819">frieze of the Parthenon</rs> as a visible <rs type="work" ref="pmb31827">
                  <hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue</hi>
               </rs>. Or one might express it in this way: if one wanted to explain the <rs type="work" ref="pmb31827">
                  <hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue</hi>
               </rs> to a deaf man, it would only be necessary to show him the <rs type="work" ref="pmb31819">frieze of the Parthenon</rs>. This new <rs type="work" subtype="implied" ref="pmb31825">book</rs> about <rs type="person" ref="pmb10806">Bach</rs> arouses so much favourable and bitterly hostile comment, chiefly on account of the strange discovery which the author claims to have made concerning the real genesis of the <rs type="work" ref="pmb31827">
                  <hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy</hi>
               </rs>. How did <rs type="person" ref="pmb10806">Bach</rs> come to it? How did it occur to him? What was the first thing to occur to him? It occurred to him to compose his own name, and he discovered that everything went beautifully, as soon as he let his name become chromatic. After the <rs type="work" ref="pmb31827">
                  <hi rend="italic">Fantasy</hi>
               </rs> breaks down into chaos, the <rs type="work" ref="pmb31827">
                  <hi rend="italic">Fugue</hi>
               </rs> begins again bravely and confidently with <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, <hi rend="italic">h</hi>, <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. As soon as one dechromatises <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, <hi rend="italic">h</hi>, <hi rend="italic">c</hi> the result is <rs type="person" ref="pmb10806">
                  <hi rend="spaced_out">Bach</hi>
               </rs>,<pb/> the composer’s name. <rs type="person" ref="pmb10806">Bach</rs> himself, as we know from an eighteenth-century <anchor type="commentary" xml:id="KT038-6">
                  <rs type="work" subtype="implied" ref="pmb30949">musical lexicon</rs>
               </anchor>, was proud of his purely musical name. He introduces it in the <rs type="work" ref="pmb31831">
                  <hi rend="italic">C sharp minor fugue</hi>
               </rs> of the <rs type="work" ref="pmb31821">
                  <hi rend="italic">Wohltemperiertes Klavier</hi>
               </rs> and in the <rs type="work" ref="pmb31829">
                  <hi rend="italic">Invention in F minor</hi> for three voices</rs>. It is in the <rs type="work" ref="pmb31827">
                  <hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy</hi>
               </rs>, however, that he first gives his name a triumphant transformation. He now makes the name with which he was born consciously his own in that he transposes the letters. He no longer merely accepts what he received at his birth, but out of <hi rend="italic">b a c h</hi> he now makes <hi rend="italic">a b h c</hi>. This means that what he passively received he is now making a free and intense activity of his own. This results in the creation of a symbol–namely, that freedom can only consist in that we not only suffer what is necessary but also do what is necessary; that we let the will of God not only act <hi rend="italic">upon</hi> us but also <hi rend="italic">through</hi> us. »<anchor type="commentary" xml:id="KT038-7">
                  <rs type="work" subtype="implied" ref="pmb31571">Make use of whatever experience comes to you!</rs>
               </anchor>« said <rs type="person" ref="pmb11461">Goethe</rs>; and always this has been the ultimate secret of all wisdom. It lies within ourselves alone to learn to master our destiny, in that we obey it. Suffering, no matter how great, will burst forth in a cry of rejoicing as soon as we courageously say »Yea« to it. Only he who resists the gods eternally remains bound. <rs type="person" ref="pmb12793">Sitte’s</rs> work is the result of profound experience. It leads us to the ultimate problems where the highest art always intermingles with ethics, but it also is rich in technical knowledge. He shows us that <rs type="person" ref="pmb10806">Bach</rs> to-day is almost universally misunderstood by pianists. They romanticise him, and have grown accustomed to treating the piano like an organ. <rs type="person" ref="pmb10806">Bach</rs> must be cleansed of the romantic accretions: he must not be played like an organ; he must be »fingered,« that is to say, played »with the weight and force of the fingers alone, without any special co-operation of the arm-muscles.« During recent years it seems as if the spirit of imperialism had likewise passed into the piano. Among pianists, too, pride of muscle was everywhere in the ascendancy. The <rs type="work" subtype="implied" ref="pmb31825">book</rs> should be welcomed as a sign that the good old German tradition is not forgotten, for through it alone can we regain our health. The real success of the book bears testimony to the vitality of the <rs type="place" ref="pmb151">German</rs> spirit. <signed>HERMANN BAHR</signed>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
